<metadata xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions" xmlns:xdt="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-datatypes"><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Washington State Department of Transportation</origin><pubdate>20120702</pubdate><title>State Route Mile Post Markers of Washington State</title><geoform>vector digital data</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Olympia, Washington, USA</pubplace><publish>Washington State Department of Transportation (WSDOT)</publish></pubinfo></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This dataset contains two sources used to determine X, Y coordinates for positions along Washington State highways perpendicular to milepost markers. Locations were collected on the fly from a moving vehicle using Global Positioning Systems (GPS) technology, and using Geographic Information Systems (GIS) processes, the Washington State Department of Transportation (WSDOT) 24k Linear Referencing System (LRS) and the WSDOT Traffic Signs Management Systems database (TSMS).</abstract><purpose>Provide location reference along Washington State Highways for such uses as: routing, vehicle tracking, emergency services, traffic safety, and WSDOT project planning and management.</purpose></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20120701</caldate><time>Unknown</time></sngdate></timeinfo><current>ground condition</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Annually</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-124.672354</westbc><eastbc>-116.863256</eastbc><northbc>49.031803</northbc><southbc>45.505186</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>Milepost</themekey><themekey>State Route</themekey><themekey>Transportation Data</themekey><themekey>Highway</themekey><themekey>Milepost Paddles</themekey><themekey>Safety</themekey><themekey>Milepost Markers</themekey><themekey>Navigation</themekey></theme><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>Washington State</placekey><placekey>WA</placekey><placekey>United States</placekey><placekey>USA</placekey><placekey>Pacific Northwest</placekey><placekey>Washington</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>Due to the diverse sources of this data, accuracy varies within the dataset and is relative to the purpose stated above. Also, this data may have changed since the publication date. If you find an error with this data and can provide updated information, please contact the GIS and Roadway Data Office at (360) 570-2363 or fax (360) 570-2400.</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Thomas A. Blake</cntper><cntorg>Washington State Department of Transportation</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Data Products Supervisor</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>physical address</addrtype><address>7345 Linderson Way SW</address><city>Tumwater</city><state>WA</state><postal>98501-7384</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>(360) 570-2363</cntvoice><cntemail>blaket@wsdot.wa.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac><datacred>
Roadway Branch, Transportation Data Office, Washington State Department of Transportation
Transportation Signs Management System, Washington State Department of Transportation
</datacred><native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.3000</native></idinfo><dataqual><complete>This dataset represents all State Routes in Washington State. However, milepost markers are not present for every mile. Milepost markers were collected in the field or from a query of the TSMS database.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>
This dataset contains two sources used to determine X,Y coordinates for positions along state highways perpendicular to milepost markers. The dataset contains a field indicating the source. Source 1 was collected with GPS from a moving vehicle as a single point. Source 2 was obtained through GIS processes using a 24k LRS and data from the Traffic Sign Management System.
Source 1 data points with a directional indicator of 'b' have an average accuracy of +/- one-hundredth of a mile (52.8 ft.).
Source 1 data points with a directional indicator of 'i' or 'd' have an average accuracy of +/- two-hundredths of a mile (105.6 ft). 
Source 2 data points have an unknown accuracy.
</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>Elevations were obtained using resource grade GPS equipment and have an average accuracy of +/- fifteen feet. Data points from source 2 data have no elevation associated with them and a placeholder of 99999.99 was used.</vertaccr><qvertpa><vertaccv>99999.99</vertaccv><vertacce>Source 2 value not applicable, null placeholder.</vertacce></qvertpa></vertacc></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>
Initial data collection was performed with GPS technology on the fly from moving vehicles.  Data was collected in the increasing and decreasing direction of travel as a single point while passing perpendicularly to each milepost marker. The milepost markers along undivided highways were collected twice, once in each direction where possible. The milepost markers along divided highways were collected once in the direction of travel, where possible.

The GPS data was post processed and exported with Pathfinder Office into a text file for each state route. New data fields were added: State Route ID (identification) and ARM (actual route mileage)  values were derived from the  WSDOT 24k LRS dataset. The increasing and decreasing files of each route were joined together geospatially using the nearest function, and two tables were produced. This data was then validated, the average distance field was created, and a single table was produced. An SRMP value was obtained using the ArmCalc module to determine the MP_value.

For source 2 mileposts, the TSMS database was queried for milepost markers. This dataset was compared to the source 1 data and duplicates were removed. ARM values were obtained from the SRMP values given in the TSMS database using ARMCalc and then placed on the WSDOT's 24k LRS. X,Y coordinates were obtained for these points using ESRI's GIS software.

The source 1 and source 2 data sets were combined into a single file, placed as an event theme using the longitude and latitude coordinate fields, and then exported as a shapefile. This shapefile was projected from GCS NAD83 to GCS NAD 83 HARN.  New NAD 83 HARN coordinates were generated with the ESRI AddXY command and loaded into the longitude and latitude fields.
</procdesc><procdate>2005</procdate><proccont><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Jason Stambaugh or Jason Moxham</cntper><cntorg>Washington State Department of Transportation, Transportation Data Office, Roadway Branch</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Transportation Planning Tech 3</cntpos><cntvoice>(360) 570-2359 Jason Stambaugh, (360) 570-2437 Jason Moxham</cntvoice><cntemail>stambaj@wsdot.wa.gov,moxhamj@wsdot.wa.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></proccont></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Changes to the geographic location of mile post markers as reported in the TSMS data base were processed using GIS software and new coordinates established.  An updated event theme was created and processed as in step one.</procdesc><procdate>20101202</procdate><proccont><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Thomas A. Blake</cntper><cntorg>Washington State Department of Transportation, GIS and Roadway Data Office</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Data Products Supervisor</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>physical address</addrtype><address>7345 Linderson Way SW</address><city>Tumwater</city><state>WA</state><postal>98501-7384</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>(360) 570-2363</cntvoice><cntemail>blaket@wsdot.wa.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></proccont></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Updates were made to the Region attribute of Milepost Markers along US 12 due to a WSDOT region boundary adjustment between the Southwest and South Central Regions</procdesc><procdate>20120624</procdate><proccont><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Thomas A. Blake</cntper><cntorg>Washington State Department of Transportation</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Data Products Supervisor</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>physical address</addrtype><address>7345 Linderson Way SW</address><city>Tumwater</city><state>WA</state><postal>98501-7384</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>(360) 570-2363</cntvoice><cntemail>blaket@wsdot.wa.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></proccont></procstep></lineage><cloud>0</cloud></dataqual><spdoinfo><direct>Vector</direct><ptvctinf><sdtsterm><sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype><ptvctcnt>7885</ptvctcnt></sdtsterm></ptvctinf></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><geograph><latres>0</latres><longres>0</longres><geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit></geograph><geodetic><horizdn>D_North_American_1983_HARN</horizdn><ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips><semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis><denflat>298.257222</denflat></geodetic></horizsys><vertdef><altsys><altres>1.000000</altres><altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc></altsys></vertdef></spref><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>wastate_mp_SPS</enttypl><enttypd>Points indicate locations perpendicular to milepost markers along Washington State Highways.</enttypd></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>AB</attrlabl><attrdef>Ahead Back Indicator, An indicator that denotes if the Linear Referencing Method (Trafficway) State Route Milepost is within a Back Mileage Equation Area</attrdef><attrdefs>Washington State Department of Transportation Data Catalog</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>A</edomv><edomvd>Ahead indicator</edomvd></edom><edom><edomv>B</edomv><edomvd>Back indicator</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>COMMENTS</attrlabl><attrdef>Comment field for use during data updates.</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>DIRECTION</attrlabl><attrdef>For data with source code of 1, indicates the direction of travel the data was collected in. For data with source code of 2, indicates the 24k LRS dataset used.</attrdef><attrdomv><edom><edomv>i</edomv><edomvd>Data collected in the increasing lane of travel with GPS or placed on a increasing 24k LRS.</edomvd></edom><edom><edomv>d</edomv><edomvd>Data collected in the decreasing lane of travel with GPS or placed on a decreasing 24k LRS.</edomvd></edom><edom><edomv>b</edomv><edomvd>Data collected in both directions of travel using GPS for a single milepost marker.</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>DISTANCE</attrlabl><attrdef>The average distance between the two positions collected using GPS for the same milepost marker.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>99999.99</edomv><edomvd>Placeholder for a null value</edomvd></edom><udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>HAE</attrlabl><attrdef>Height Above Ellipsoid - The vertical distance in feet above or below a reference ellipsoid.  For WSDOT this reference ellipsoid is designated WGS84.</attrdef><attrdefs>Roadway Location Data Dictionary</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>99999.99</edomv><edomvd>Null value placeholder</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>LATITUDE</attrlabl><attrdef>The degree of latitude above the equator represented by a 2 digit number of degrees from 00 to 90 and fractions of degrees with 6 decimal places.  Only applies to the northern hemisphere. Values in this field are NAD83 HARN.</attrdef><attrdefs>Roadway Location Data Dictionary</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>LONGITUDE</attrlabl><attrdef>The degree of longitude west of Greenwich, England, represented by a 3 digit number of degrees from 000 through 180 and decimal fractions of degrees with 6 decimal places.  East longitudes are not included. Values in this field are NAD83 HARN</attrdef><attrdefs>Roadway Location Data Dictionary</attrdefs></attr><attr><attrlabl>MP_VALUE</attrlabl><attrdef>Milepost Value indicates the number that appears on the milepost marker.</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>OBJECTID</attrlabl><attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>REF_DATE</attrlabl><attrdef>Date the individual points were valid.</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl>REGION</attrlabl><attrdef>Region - The geographic and administrative areas of responsibility of the Washington State Department of Transportation within the State of Washington.</attrdef><attrdefs>Washington State Department of Transportation Data Catalog</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>NC</edomv><edomvd>North Central Region - Washington State Department of Transportation</edomvd></edom><edom><edomv>OL</edomv><edomvd>Olympic Region - Washington State Department of Transportation</edomvd></edom><edom><edomv>NW</edomv><edomvd>Northwest Region - Washington State Department of Transportation</edomvd></edom><edom><edomv>SW</edomv><edomvd>Southwest Region - Washington State Department of Transportation</edomvd></edom><edom><edomv>SC</edomv><edomvd>South Central Region - Washington State Department of Transportation</edomvd></edom><edom><edomv>EA</edomv><edomvd>Eastern Region - Washington State Department of Transportation</edomvd></edom><udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl><attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef><attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>SOURCE</attrlabl><attrdef>Indicates how the X,Y coordinates where obtained.</attrdef><attrdomv><edom><edomv>1</edomv><edomvd>Data collected with GPS</edomvd></edom><edom><edomv>2</edomv><edomvd>X,Y coordinates derived from the 24k LRS, using values from the Traffic Signs Management System database</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>SR</attrlabl><attrdef>Washington State Highways are defined by the following: State Route (SR) number, Related Roadway Type (RRT) and Related Roadway Qualifier (RRQ). These three descriptors uniquely identify and every piece of the highway system in Washington State. For definitions of SR, RRT and RRQ see the WSDOT metadata for the GIS Roadlog dataset</attrdef><attrdefs>The Washington State Highway Log</attrdefs></attr></detailed><overview><eaover>This data set contains milepost marker values, elevations, WSDOT region indicators, data source information, State Route indicators.</eaover></overview></eainfo><distinfo><distrib><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>Washington State Department of Transportation, Office of Information Technology</cntorg><cntper>Jordyn Mitchell</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>GIS Database  Administrator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>PO Box 47430</address><city>Olympia</city><state>WA</state><postal>98504-7430</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>360-705-7645</cntvoice><cntemail>mitchejo@wsdot.wa.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib><distliab>The Washington State Department of Transportation shall not be liable for any activity involving this data with regard to lost profits or savings or any other consequential damages; or the fitness for use of the data for a particular purpose; or the installation of the data, its use, or the results obtained.</distliab><stdorder><fees>none</fees><ordering>Download individual data sets from http://www.wsdot.wa.gov/mapsdata/geodatacatalog/default.htm</ordering></stdorder><availabl><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>Unknown</caldate><time>Unknown</time></sngdate></timeinfo></availabl></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20120624</metd><metrd></metrd><metfrd></metfrd><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Thomas A. Blake</cntper><cntorg>Washington State Department of Transportation</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Data Products Supervisor</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>physical address</addrtype><address>7345 Linderson Way SW</address><city>Tumwater</city><state>WA</state><postal>98501-7384</postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>(360) 570-2363</cntvoice><cntemail>blaket@wsdot.wa.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></metc><metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv><mettc>local time</mettc><metac>none</metac><metuc>none</metuc><metsi><metsc>Unclassified</metsc></metsi><metextns><onlink>http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink><metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof></metextns></metainfo></metadata>